<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:distill="https://distill.pub/journal/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>vgherard</title>
    <link>https://vgherard.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Valerio Gherardi's Personal Website
</description>
    <generator>Distill</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics</title>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Gherardi</dc:creator>
      <link>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/thermodynamics</link>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Miscellaneous notes about concepts of Thermodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="systems"&gt;Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system is the part of the universe that is the focus of our
thermodynamic description. The state of a system is characterized by its
macroscopic coordinates, the specification of which forms part of the
experimental input to the thermodynamic description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system’s surroundings is the part of the universe that interacts
(that is exchanges energy) with the system. The characterization of the
surroundings may also include the specification of some macroscopic
coordinates (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; external pressure, force fields, temperature
of thermal reservoirs…).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="work"&gt;Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notion of “work” in Thermodynamics generally refers that fraction
of energy exchanged by a system during a thermodynamic process, which
&lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be produced by a change in the potential energy of some
macroscopic object interacting with the system. In order to
operationalize this intuition, we may assume that for any thermodynamic
process there exist equivalent experimental conditions, under which the
system passes through the same sequence of intermediate configurations
connecting the initial and final states, and under which the performance
of work is entirely implemented by the raising or lowering of a weight
in a gravitational field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the formal point of view, the quantitative expression of work in
any given circumstance should be considered as an external input to the
general theory. This may come either from direct measurement or from
more detailed theories (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; mechanics, electromagnetism),
always in accordance with the above operative definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be stressed that thermodynamics does not provide by itself
any means to determine the “equivalent experimental conditions” referred
to in the operative definition above, nor any guidance for calculating
work from first principles. The ultimate test of whether a theoretical
or empirical assessment of work is correct is the consistency of the
resulting thermodynamic description for the system under
consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="laws-of-thermodynamics"&gt;Laws of thermodynamics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="first-law"&gt;First law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exist experimental conditions, called &lt;em&gt;“thermal
insulation”&lt;/em&gt;, under which the work performed along a certain
transformation depends only on the initial and final states of the
system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here and below, the wording “adiabatic” will always refer to thermal
insulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operative definitions of &lt;em&gt;internal energy&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;heat&lt;/em&gt; make use, in addition to the First Law, of the following
additional postulate, sometimes referred to as the “Comparison
Principle” &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Lieb and Yngvason 1999)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any two states of a thermodynamic system, there exists an
adiabatic process that starts in one of the two states and ends in the
other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then define internal energy as the work required to bring a
system to a given state from a reference zero-energy state, in adiabatic
conditions. Once internal energy is defined, we define the heat absorbed
during a process as the difference between the internal energy change
and the work performed on the system. These definitions are
conventionally summarized by the equation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;\[
\Delta U = W+Q.(\#eq:FirstLaw)
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="transitivity-of-thermal-equilibrium-zero-th-law"&gt;Transitivity of
thermal equilibrium (“Zero-th” Law)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two systems are said to be in &lt;em&gt;thermal contact&lt;/em&gt; if they may
exchange energy in the form of heat. When two systems, which are
individually in equilibrium, are brought into thermal contact, they will
generally undergo a series of changes, until reaching a new equilibrium
state. At this point, we may say that the systems are in &lt;em&gt;thermal
equilibrium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an empirical fact that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If two systems are in thermal equilibrium with a third system, they
are also in thermal equilibrium with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we take, as a probe for thermal equilibrium, a system which is
essentially one-dimensional, such as an ideal gas held at a standard
pressure, we can then conclude that thermal equilibrium can be
characterized by a single number, an &lt;em&gt;empirical temperature&lt;/em&gt;. The
temperature of a system would be measured by the volume reached by our
ideal gas probe once put in thermal contact with such system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle is sometimes referred to as the “Zero-th” Law of
Thermodynamics, because it is essential to the definition of
temperature, whose concept is taken for granted throughout the usual
expositions of Thermodynamics. In our formulation, the First Law
precedes this principle from a logical point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="r distill-force-highlighting-css"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent"
entry-spacing="0"&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-LY1" class="csl-entry"&gt;
Lieb, Elliott H., and Jakob Yngvason. 1999. &lt;span&gt;“The Physics and
Mathematics of the Second Law of Thermodynamics.”&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;Physics
Reports&lt;/em&gt; 310 (1): 1–96. https://doi.org/&lt;a
href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0370-1573(98)00082-9"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0370-1573(98)00082-9&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
      <distill:md5>1549d9045379792413da579189d635c2</distill:md5>
      <guid>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/thermodynamics</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum Likelihood</title>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Gherardi</dc:creator>
      <link>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/maximum-likelihood</link>
      <description>Maximum Likelihood</description>
      <guid>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/maximum-likelihood</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Dispersion Models</title>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Gherardi</dc:creator>
      <link>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/exponential-dispersion-models</link>
      <description>Exponential Dispersion Models</description>
      <guid>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/exponential-dispersion-models</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrap</title>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Gherardi</dc:creator>
      <link>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/bootstrap</link>
      <description>Bootstrap</description>
      <guid>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/bootstrap</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ordinary Least Squares</title>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Gherardi</dc:creator>
      <link>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/ordinary-least-squares</link>
      <description>Ordinary Least Squares</description>
      <guid>https://vgherard.github.io/notebooks/ordinary-least-squares</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
